Xavier University Capital Gifts Campaigns collection
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University Capital Gifts Campaigns collection
1915-2011
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)
2.5 linear feet (5 boxes)
This is a collection of documents relating to the various capital gifts campaigns conducted by Xavier University. It encompasses the St. Xavier Diamond Jubilee Fund (1915-1920) through the To See Great Wonders campaign (2006-2011).
XUA-56
History of Xavier University Capital Gifts Campaigns
Xavier University has conducted various capital gifts campaigns throughout its history. This collection reflects those campaigns initiated in the Twentieth Century and going forward. Capital gifts campaigns are differentiated from the annual fund raising activities also conducted by the university.
Capital gifts campaigns for the time period encompassing this collection were: 1. Diamond Jubilee (1915), for the building of Alumni Hall; 2. Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) that celebrated the 400th anniversary of the founding of the Society of Jesus, and the 100th anniversary of the establishment of the Jesuits in Cincinnati. Its purpose was to raise money for academic scholarships, for endowed scholarships, for endowed professorial chairs, and to eliminate university debt; 3. Xavier University Fund and Good Will Campaign (1945), for endowments and building projects; 4. Long Range Development Program (1956) that celebrated the 125th anniversary of the establishment of the Athenaeum, for scholarships, fellowships, and building construction; 5. Xavier University Advancement Fund (1972); 6. Sesquicentennial Fund celebrating the 150th anniversary of the establishment of the Athenaeum, for a new College of Business Administration building and endowments; 7. Cornerstone Campaign (1987), for scholarships, endowments, and building activities, including new science facilities; 8. Century Campaign (1996), for endowments, building renovations, and the building of a convocation center (later named the Cintas Center); 9. To See Great Wonders(2006), for the construction of the Hoff Academic Quadrangle, other construction projects, endowments and to increase the annual fund.
Scope and Content
This collection includes correspondence, brochures, reports and other materials relating to the various capital gifts campaigns conducted by Xavier University (formerly St. Xavier College) from 1915 to the early 21st Century.
Statement of Arrangement
Materials are arranged by folder chronologically by the period of the individual capital gifts campaign.
Restrictions on Access
Some materials may have restricted access. Please contact the archives staff.
Accruals
Additions to this collection are anticipated.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Educational fund raising--Ohio
Organizations/Corporations:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)-- Finance
Detailed Description of The Collection
- St. Xavier Diamond Jubilee Fund, 1915 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  This folder contains a 1915 appeal to Xavier alumnae and friends to support the campaign.
  For further information concerning this campaign, see XUA-53 Xavier University Master Building Plans collection.
  The St. Xavier Diamond Jubilee Fund (1915-1920) was initiated in celebration of the 75th anniversary of the arrival of the Jesuits at St. Xavier College in 1840. It was St. Xavier College's first public appeal for financial support. The campaign was sponsored by the St. Xavier Diamond Jubilee Fund Committee with a goal of $75,000.00. The purpose of the campaign included funding for new buildings for the Avondale campus. The Fund paid the major portion of the cost of Alumni Science Hall (later renamed Edgecliff Hall). Francis Heiermann, S.J. was the president of St. Xavier College at this time.
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Preparatory and Introductory Records, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  This folder contains a campaign publicity brochure.
  The Jesuit Centennial Fund celebrated the 400th anniversary of the founding of the Society of Jesus (1540) and the 100th anniversary of the establishment of the Jesuits in Cincinnati (1840). This fund was sponsored by the Jesuit Centennial Fund Committee. The committee's honorary chair was John T. McNicholas, the Archbishop of Cincinnati. The general chair was Charles F. Williams.
  The purpose of the campaign was to raise money for academic scholarships, for endowed scholarships, for endowed professorial chairs and to eliminate university debt.
  Celestin Steiner, S.J. was the president of Xavier University at this time.
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Correspondence, Reports, Lists, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Correspondence, Reports, Lists, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Correspondence, Reports, Lists, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Correspondence, Reports, Lists, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Correspondence, Reports, Lists, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Correspondence, Reports, Lists, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Promotional Letters by Celestin Steiner, S.J., 1941 April (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Lists of Prospective Donors, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Lists of Prospective Donors, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Lists of Prospective Donors, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Lists of Donors and Donations, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Letters of Gratitude to Donors, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Letter to Alumni / Alumni Captains' Reports, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Correspondence with Alumni Captains, 1941 March (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Jesuit Centennial Fund (1940) Correspondence with Alumni Captains, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Xavier University Fund and Good Will Campaign (1945-1952), 1945-1947; undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  This folder contains campaign related correspondence and published materials.
  The purpose of the Xavier University Fund and Good Will Campaign was to raise $ 450,000.00 for the Endowment Fund and $ 550,000.00 for building projects. Proposed buildings included an assembly hall, an additional classroom, and dormitory rooms for out of town students. The campaign was sponsored by the Citizens' Committee, Richard E. LeBlond chair. Celestin Steiner, S.J. was the president of Xavier at this time.
- Xavier University Fund and Good Will Campaign (1945-1952), 1951; undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  This folder contains published campaign materials.
- Long Range Development Program for Xavier University (1956-1957) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  For further information and pictures concerning this campaign, see archival collection XUA-53 Master Buildings Plans collection.
  The Long Range Development Program for Xavier University was initiated in celebration of the 125th anniversary of the establishment of the Athenaeum (1831), the forerunner of St. Xavier College and Xavier University. The purpose of the campaign was to financially support additional faculty, scholarships, and building construction.
- Xavier University Advancement Fund (1972-1977), 1967; 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  This folder contains correspondence and memos.
  See Xavier Archives collection XUA-18, Planning and Development Committee records for preparatory materials that place the Xavier University Advancement Fund effort in context.
  The goal of the Xavier University Advancement Fund was to raise 30 million dollars over a ten year period. The campaign actually raised a total of $ 8,600,000.00. A Planning and Development Committee was established by Xavier president Paul O'Connor, S.J. in 1968 to prepare for this campaign (see Xavier archives collection XUA-18, Planning and Development Committee records). The campaign was phased out in 1976.
- Xavier University Advancement Fund (1972-1977) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  This folder contains meeting minutes and memorandums.
- Xavier University Advancement Fund (1972-1977) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  This folder contains brochures and other printed information concerning the campaign.
- Xavier University Advancement Fund (1972-1977), 1972 August-December (Box 3, Folder 7)
  This folder contains correspondence, meeting notes, and reports.
- Xavier University Advancement Fund (1972-1977), 1973 January-June (Box 4, Folder 1)
  This folder contains correspondence, reports, and meeting minutes.
- Xavier University Advancement Fund (1972-1977), 1973 June-December (Box 4, Folder 2)
  This folder includes the "Advancement Fund Report" (Brakeley, John Price Jones, Inc.) and the document "A Presentation from Xavier University for an Enriched Montessori Program."
- Xavier University Advancement Fund (1972-1977), 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  This folder includes Xavier University Advancement Fund serial publications.
- Sesquicentennial Campaign (1976-1981) Brochures and Printed Materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  This folder includes the following items: Brochure "For a Greater Tomorrow-- a Task Today"; Brochure "Short Case for a Big Need"; Brochure "Support the X Factor"
  For records concerning The Five Year Plan (1976-1981) which accompanied the Sesquicentennial Campaign, see archival collection XUA-57, Long Range Strategic Planning collection.
  The Sesquicentennial Campaign was conducted in celebration of the 150th anniversary of the establishment of the Athenaeum (1831), the forerunner of St. Xavier College and Xavier University. The purposes of the campaign were to build a new College of Business Administration building and to further fund endowments for the library, scholarships, faculty development, facilities renovation and instructional equipment. The campaign raised $8,389,683.00. Robert W. Mulligan, S.J. was president of the university at that time.
- Sesquicentennial Campaign (1976-1981) Correspondence and Reports, 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  This folder includes some correspondence and various Xavier printed publications in support of the Sesquicentennial Campaign.
  For a copy of the Master Plan Report of KZF, Inc. consult the archival collection XUA-53, Xavier University Master Buildings Plans collection. For records concerning the strategic planning which preceded this campaign, consult the archival collection XUA-57, Xavier University Long Range Strategic Planning collection.
  The Cornerstone Campaign had as its purpose to raise funds to create endowed scholarships, endowed professorial chairs, and endowed faculty development. It also sought to enhance the university's science facilities by new construction and renovation. The campaign raised nearly 31.5 million dollars. Albert DiUlio, S.J. was president of the university at that time.
- Sesquicentennial Campaign (1976-1981) Reports and Printed Materials, 1976-1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  This folder contains the following items: 1. Five Year Plan, 1976-1981, Preliminary Projections (September, 1976); 2. Five-Year Projection of Budgetary Needs for the Division of Student Development, 1976-1981; 3. Five-Year Projection of Budgetary Needs for the Business-Finance Division, 1976-77 to 1980-81 (August, 1976); 4. Various university serial publications.
- Cornerstone Campaign (1987-1992) Case Statement and Other Documents, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  This folder includes "The Campaign for Xavier: the Case Statement".
- Cornerstone Campaign (1987-1992) Opening Celebration Brochure and Other Materials, 1989; undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  This folder includes campaign publicity materials.
- Cornerstone Campaign (1987-1992) Reports and Publications, 1987-1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  This folder contains the following: 1. Final Report: Xavier University's Cornerstone Campaign, August 1986 to June 1992 (March 1, 1993); 2. Xavier News Release (May 4, 1989); 3. Cornerstone issues (newsletter for the campaign); 4. Texts of various presentations.
- Century Campaign (1996-2001), 1996-1999; undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  This folder contains: 1. Various program leaflets relating to public events regarding the campaign; 2. Issues of Milestones (the campaign newsletter); 3. Information concerning a Century Campaign history video.
  For documents and records concerning the strategic plan, XU 2000, which accompanied this campaign, consult the collection XUA-57, Xavier University Long Range Strategic Planning collection. For documents concerning the construction of the new buildings during this time, consult XUA-53, Xavier University Master Building Plans collection. For information on the Gallagher Student Center and the Cintas Center see also XUA-54, Xavier University Campus Buildings and Properties collection.
  The Century Campaign was meant to prepare Xavier University for its entrance into the Twenty-First Century. The campaign raised over 125 million dollars. James Hoff, S.J. was president of the university at that time. The purposes of the campaign were numerous, including the creation of endowed scholarships and professorships, the creation of an endowment for faculty development, the renovation of Hinkle, Schmidt and Alumni Science Halls, the renovation of the Academic Mall and Residential Mall, the creation of the Xavier Green; the renovation of the University Student Center, and the construction of a Convocation Center (later known as the Cintas Center).
- Century Campaign (1996-2001), undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  This folder contains various campaign publicity brochures, Century Campaign buttons, and an information packet from the Xavier Office of Marketing and Public Relations concerning the campaign.
  For documents and records concerning the strategic plan, XU2000, which accompanied this campaign, consult archival collection XUA-57, Xavier University Long Range Strategic Planning collection. For documents concerning the construction of the new buildings during this time, consult archival collection XUA-53, Xavier University Master Building Plans collection. For further information on the Gallagher Student Center and the Cintas Center, consult XUA-54, Xavier University Campus Buildings and Properties collection.
- Century Campaign (1996-2001), 1994-2001 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  This folder contains correspondence, lists, news releases, news clippings and other materials concerning the campaign.
- Century Campaign (1996-2001), 1994-2001; undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  This folder contains: 1. "A Confidential Report on the Survey of a Representative Sample of the Constituency of Xavier University (Frick Associates, May 18, 1994); 2. Xavier News Release (June 18,1998); 3. Correspondence; 4. Copy of Powerpoint: "Xavier University."
- To See Great Wonders Campaign (2006-2011), 2006-2010; undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  This folder contains campaign publicity literature, a campaign key ring, and other items related to the campaign.
  For documents and records concerning the strategic planning which accompanied this campaign, consult XUA-57, Xavier University Long Range Strategic Planning collection. For documents and records concerning the construction of new buildings during this time, consult XUA-53, Xavier University Master Building Plans collection. For information on Fenwick Place see XUA-54, Xavier University Campus Buildings and Properties collection.
  To See Great Wonders: the Campaign for Xavier (2006-2001) had multiple purposes: to construct/remodel the Hoff Academic Quadrangle (the Conaton Learning Center, Smith Hall, renovate McDonald Library and renovate Alter Hall); to construct the new Campus Gateway at St. Francis Xavier Way and Dana Avenue; to construct the Fenwick Place Residence and Dining Complex; to create the Campus Square; to increase the university endowment; and to increase the annual fund. The campaign raised 201 million dollars. Michael J. Graham, S.J. was the president of the university at that time.
- To See Great Wonders Campaign (2006-2011), undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  This folder contains campaign publicity information packets.
- To See Great Wonders Campaign (2006-2011), undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
- To See Great Wonders Campaign (2006-2011), undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  This folder contains informational packets concerning naming opportunities, building information, and other promotional materials.